[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
so welcome to the stoa everyone i'm
peter limberg the steward of the stoa
and um today we
are doing something a little different
here uh something called embodied
book club uh and the book is collective
presencing and uh author of the book is
here uh rhea bach
and ria uh has been with the stoa
almost since the beginning uh i think
there's like 25 sessions
uh have happened so far of collective
presence uh
which happens every friday at 12 p.m
eastern time
and uh i looked at my archives uh so uh
ria actually
emailed me on april 9th after reading
one of my weird journals
and then it just felt like it was meant
to be
because a few people like richard
bartlett and one and i were mentioning
ria's work to me and i've been aware of
it for a while
and so i invited her on and then it just
clicked
and then reading her book i read the
first line of the book
in this book you will find none of the
gloom and doom scenarios that crowd
so many books articles and websites
these days i prefer to dispense with
these and focus instead on what is
possible
and that feels so aligned with um what's
happening here
at the stone the strange attractor
that's drawing us together
and it's really a space that to hold
complexity
together i will hand
over to monas right now
hi everybody um yeah
so of course uh welcome
to the stowaway it's a digital space
where we can gather and talk about what
matters most right now
at the knife's edge of what is happening
right
so the embodied book club is a little
bit of a
a different take on what we want to do
and
i'm going to spend as little time as
possible
um talking about you know there's
there's not
too much structure to it um this is uh
this is the first two chapters i'm going
to hand over to
to ria to just frame it for us you'll
get to a part where we will
just touch on a few pieces of
information
and then i'll quickly share that with
you guys and then uh you know share my
screen just show how to get to
some some other things easily and
quickly for future sessions as well
and then we'll dive right back into it
so that we can use
the little time we have as effectively
as possible
all right ria you can take it away
wow welcome everyone
i had a little shock somewhere half the
week that peter said there's
40 people and probably 50 by the end of
the week i'm like
oh okay
but welcome everyone i know quite a few
of you and some new names that's fine
um
i want to start with thanks to peter
as he gave a good platform to collective
presencing
and ongoing and actually this
manus who kind of made this happen this
book club happened like
do all the work behind the scenes and
then do the technical hosting
and i want to point out also helen who
is here
and who was actually the editor of the
book and
my housemate and friend and
also was present in the co-creation of
all the
content so without all these
people and many more uh
the book would not have been there um
i want to speak a bit to the embodied
book club
um i've never done a book club
um i don't know how it should look like
so um it might look different than how
you thought it
would be should be um but from the
beginning
when this idea was ripening
i wanted to avoid
that it would become like a mental space
only
like where we start to argue about
certain topics
and so that's why we came up with that
name of
embodied book club
i want to try here and many of you have
been in the practice already
one thing that we can hold
and create that same kind of embodied
presence
as what the whole book is about
um and
that when we speak and also when you're
reading
um that we
notice what's going on in ourselves in
our bodies
um what kind of responses do we have
to what we read or what people are
saying
here and
that's why for the ones who have been on
the
idea boards which manus
will explain a bit more
in that second column there is indeed
about
how did your body respond to certain
sentences or paragraphs or um
so also when we're going to speak here
for now and all the sessions um
invite for yourself like
to speak also
what is in your body like are you
excited or is your attention floating
away when you read something
or uh maybe
you read a sentence and you stare at it
and you're not
getting it or
so all that we really want to invite
in here as also meaningful
uh so this is not just only about
let's say conceptual ideas um
but also all the rest of what is alive
in us
um so and it's uh
yeah we have six sessions we have nine
chapters so i had to cram them in a bit
um
and i i'm sure we are not going to cover
everything
we will see how it goes it's for every
one of us it's an experiment
uh for the store for me for uh
all of you um
probably different sessions will have
different formats
um because i will prepare
along the way um
and i give now the word to manus to
actually explain a bit
of all the behind the scenes
where we can actually communicate and
before we go into check-in yeah
over to you
all right can everybody
see my screen i'm quickly sharing it
just to show visually
what i want to show you yeah all right
fantastic
so when opening the the stower website
and going down to
uh the wisdom jamie under the embodied
book club session
there's a second link that peter
put for us here that link will open
the information for the book club on
this link
we just put basic information that dates
which chapters we will be reading
i'm just going to zoom in a little bit
more and
very important here's the links to the
sticky boards
um when you click on this link it'll
open
something that looks like this and uh
anybody can you know as they're reading
like the titles of the columns say you
know what comes up for you
your attention is drawn to something or
you
you sense you know something in your
body that
that's that's coming up um or
perhaps something you'd like
clarification on or question
that that you have about um you can you
know add your note here uh we can also
very interestingly uh
you can upvote others notes this is one
of the ways that we can
also interact with each other through
this part of the experiment
of of doing it this way and um
yeah that is that is actually the i
guess the
the basics then uh we also created
a
i'm gonna put a link here in the in the
chat for us
uh we also created a chat channel on
discord
uh here is the invitation in
the text chat that uh when you
open that then you have the discord
application
you open the store server on the left
hand side there's a lot of chat channels
here that you can interact with the
the stellar community when you scroll
down a little bit you will see there is
this section called the sandbox
and under sandbox there is a collective
presence in uh channel that we have and
feel free to further the discussion
through the week here um
you know as we as we progress um and
this is open and this will be ongoing
but just to jump in there um if you're
it's your first time on the discord uh
you're not going to see any of those
you're going to have to go to the rule
section i believe
and then click the thumbs up right there
and then all that
opens up for you awesome thank you
peter for that all right and uh
yeah i think uh did i miss anything i
think that was
that was it from my side i don't know if
we want to jump in
yeah the experiment is a bit that
if i can see what is actually kept
capturing your attention or which
questions come up
um that i have some input to look at
how to actually design the next session
that's the idea behind it and we will
see if it works
um it's
an experiment as we said um
yeah as we are so many many um
i've been sitting the last couple of
hours
um how do how do we do this
in the same kind of energy
and intention that we normally have
we're not going to do a check-in with 40
people speaking
and still there is something about
paying attention to everyone who is here
and one of the ideas i came up with is
might be nice that if we
click on our names and
rename ourselves and add
the country after your name
so now we have so you click on your name
and then you can rename
and then see where we are all from at
least we get
an idea more or less
yeah from india
and usa and scotland and
more canada more u.s and so on
i think that's nice
very very many from the us and canada
so thank you for that and
um
so through whatever happens here i want
to invite
all of us to
to really
pay attention to body
emotion sensing
mind as possible
[Music]
also when we ask you to do something
like what we just did
just
invitation to stay as much in presence
and grounding or centering or whatever
you call it
for you um
and as a check-in um
we're just going to use the zoom
chat and
with this question as you enter this
group
and this whole process of reading
the book and these sessions
what question or what
and or feeling is
most alive in you right now
so just give it some time you don't need
to
rush into an answer but
what question or feeling
is most alive in you right now just give
it one or two sentences
and then we can just all read that
in the chat
sure
what
hmm
yeah and just
i know for some it can be overwhelming
to have so much input um
but the invitation
is to
to actually make your presence and your
centering or
grounding make that a priority
um if 40 answers
is overwhelming then just you don't read
them
that's a lot
oh
okay thank you
and i just invite you to
be as present as you can with yourself
and just
look at the whatever 40 50
squares on the screen
and just realize how we are
connecting across the globe
um
what i'm going to do next is just speak
for uh maybe 10 minutes or so
what i find is or the
crucial or essential essentials
of chapter one and two and
i go with the assumption that everyone
has read chapter one of do
that means i'm not going to repeat
everything what i've written there
so i'm not going to explain it all
and but even if you haven't read it yet
or there was somebody
on the idea boards who said like my body
doesn't let me read it can i still
extend
you sure just listen in that's not a
problem
so i want to
articulate what to me are the two main
ideas
and for each chapter or
first the two of chapter one let me say
it that way
and the first is
that i think
that everyone and i mean really everyone
has the capacity
to sense to have that capacity
of sensing energies that are not to be
captured
by touch or seeing or hearing
but that we can pick up
other signals let's say
and we do that all the time
everywhere we go and
what we want to do with collective
processing is
actually become more aware
of them of that of what we
notice in the
more subtle um
either atmosphere or
um i mean that's the easiest thing
i think to
to relate to you but
it's also from our mainstream life
are we actually slowing down enough so
that we actually notice it
what what we actually do notice
unconsciously
and and then of course the next step
is and when we notice
do we actually integrate it in our lives
so that it is not something we do
let's say sitting on a meditation
question because that's an easy
example how do we integrate
what we notice and what has meaning
um in our daily lives
step by step
and that's the second part is also
related with that
um
i named it in the book that it's a
process
of becoming present it's not that you
say oh now i'm present and
i'm present for the next i don't know
48 hours or something
many times it's gone by the next three
minutes
or whatever depends on what you
encounter
in your life but
the point is
i guess everyone here has done trainings
meditation mindfulness practices
whatever practices you have done
how can you integrate it in daily life
like
do you know what is your personal
route back to center
or back to grounding
even when you're in conflict with your
partner
or when you read some awful news
which we have many of
um do you know
what you do do you know yourself enough
how you get back to center back to
grounding
and how you can apply whatever
practices you have trained how you apply
that
here and now and
that's that's like the crucial part of
the first chapter um
the first chapter is about me and myself
and then the chapters move from me
uh more outwards you could say
so for me the for chapter two which is
about
i and you so let's say in relationship
with one other person
what i find most important to name is um
i made a distinction in the book
but because many people's
or let's say in many new age
circles where i was in long time ago
it's always like the ego is bad but
being a psychologist and a therapist
i don't like to call it ego i call them
our habitual responses because
you need a healthy ego to survive in the
world
and
i do want to point out that these
patterns and the shadow
as most of you know like
it's not anything that's bad
it's just
if i could just
have a magic wand sometimes
and just say it's just what it is i mean
they came into being
as a dynamic to
to help ourselves to actually survive
in whatever circumstances we were
and so it's not anything that should be
looked how you say that and looked up
upon or something like
it just be
i would say friendly to these parts
the habits we have even if you really
don't like them
and still understand deeply
that they came into being out of a
necessity
and and
the other side is
also look at others with
their patterns and some of them we might
not like at all
as also patterns
that came into being because of their
circumstances
yeah and it might be very unconscious
and there might be generations involved
and all that but
can we also look with that kind of
mildness to others
and
um so that's
all i'm going to say now about
the content of these chapters
and i want to do an experiment with all
of you and we i know we are many
um but it didn't
feel like let's go into breakout rooms
and all that
um i want to invite us
with the questions that are present that
we can actually
use our sensing as we do
in the practice like
am i called to speak a question
um is it bubbling up in me
so that i feel like okay i can bring it
um so i'm not
collecting questions in the chat and
then say okay i choose this one and this
one and this one
um i just want to
invite us into the practice with the
questions
and i also want to invite us
um i'm not i'm not the expert
um there's many people who have been in
spaces like this
um or
in the same in the practice already
of collective presencing
so let's all
tune our senses
to when we speak
either a question or a response does
need to be an
answer could be a response that's
meaningful
um and let's see how that goes
um i know it's an experiment with so
many people
um but we can try um
and as manus was
so good of already opening that discord
channel we can have more conversations
with
questions and responses over there in
the next
couple of days
i think with that i'm just
put my talking piece in the middle as we
normally do
in these in this practice
and see like
what question is really alive
and that is alive in you and might
most likely be alive also in others
and see where we go from there
and i want to keep it to chapter one and
two
if possible yeah